=======================================================
CS3230: Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Spring 2015
Common Mistakes in HW1
=======================================================

Following are some common mistakes in HW1.

For S1: (graded by Ken Sung)
(a) Some students report 8 for (floor(log n)) instead of 9 (ceiling(log n)).
[Comment by LHW: One simple way to verify it is to do the repeated-divide-by-two process to check your answer.]

(b) (iii) Some students report log n instead of n.
[Comment by LHW: Sometimes, the exact value of something is NOT a precise number, but a range (in this case between lg(n) and n. In that case, you give the range. And from there, you can specify the worst-case of n.]


For S2: (graded by Shunhao)
S2a)
- A large number of students gave only the stable matchings without the explanation, or the explanation without the matching. Do note that this question actually has two parts.
- For the explanation, male-optimality, female-optimality does not explain the uniqueness of the stable pairing. On the other hand, male-optimality, male-pessimality does.


S2b)
- About half of the people get this right. There are only so many ways you can write out the tables.
- One thing to note is that this question has NOTHING to do with the Gale-Shapely algorithm. Many try to explain why it is that when the boys propose and when the girls propose, both are stable. There is no point in doing so.

When there are two boys and two girls, there are only two possible pairings:
a-A, b-B AND a-B, b-A.
The objective is to ensure that both these pairings are stable.


S2c)
A surprisingly high percentage of students found an arrangement that requires 7 proposals.
However, very few were able to correctly explain why 7 is the maximum.

- Many try to do so by trying to describe a "worst-case scenario", then explaining why this "worst-case" requires 7 proposals. However, a big hole in the argument is not explaining why this "worst-case" described is actually the worst case. This is actually very difficult to do, and this should not be the preferred method of constructing the proof.

- Many quoted this formula they got from the internet (StackOverflow, MIT, Wikipedia), that the max. number of proposals is n(n-1) + 1. Just giving the formula and trying to wrap some explanation around it is not going earn any marks.
- Some simply copy the explanation from those sources above. Those proofs thankfully leave out some important details (e.g. why there can only be 1 man who proposes to n women).
 [Comment added by LHW: A thousand people doing something, does not necessarily mean it is RIGHT. If a proof is needed, then it is needed. A thousand people not doing it, does not make it unnecessary.]

- Finally, and most importantly, many students explain the wrong thing. The question is asking "Why is it impossible to construct a preference list that requires more than 7 proposals?". Many students answer the question "How do you construct a preference list that reaches the worst case of 7 proposals?". The 7-proposal example in the answer is enough for the latter. However, to explain the former, you do not need to explain how a preference list of 7 proposals is constructed! You simply need to explain, preferably without examples, why 8 or more is impossible.

Here are some good "skeletons" for the proof. (Note that we do not need to show how it reaches its seventh proposal. We can assume that it is possible for the sake of this proof.)
A)
Suppose that the gale-shapely algorithm is on its seventh proposal.
- <Insert proof content here>
Therefore the algorithm will terminate at this point. Thus the 8th proposal will never happen.

B)
Suppose that 8 men have proposed in the gale-shapely algorithm.
- <Insert proof content here>
Thus there is a contradiction. Thus it is not possible for 8 (or more) proposals to be made.

A full proof of the question is given at the bottom of this file.


S3: (graded by NNN)
- Forget to justify why 4 rooms in (a) is optimal (-1 mark);
- Give the rooms' status after 13 event points instead of giving room assignment (-1 mark);
- Not stating which sorting algorithm to use to get THETA(nlogn) worst-case (-1 mark)
- say that Quicksort is O(nlogn) [worst-case is THETA(n^2)] (-1 mark)
- say that General BST is O(logn) per operation. [worst-case is THETA(n)] (-1 mark);
- Give too brief/ too high-level answer
- Give too long answer!

I think some students just tried to use any data structure they know 
(bBST, PQ, heap, hash, AVL tree,...) to get O(nlogn) time. 
Many students love AVL tree and PQ (they use AVL tree/PQ to store the set T)!
Maybe next time we need to ask them give implementation 
pseudo code with data structures they use.



==============================
[Proof for S2c]

Proof that we cannot have more than 7 proposals for any arrangement.

Suppose we are currently on the seventh proposal.
By the pigeonhole principle, each of the 3 women has been proposed to at least once.
We note that once a woman is matched, she only trades up after that. i.e. she will never become unmatched again.
Thus at this point, all women are matched.
Thus at this point, all men are matched.
Thus there is no free man. The algorithm must terminate at this point.
Thus there cannot be an 8th proposal. //


This proof can be easily generalised to the general case. (To prove that we cannot have more than n(n-1) + 1 proposals for any arrangement)

